A Guide to the Walter Frank Papers 1925-1970
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Walter Frank Papers 1925-1970
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10951
480 items
The Walter Frank collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, printed material and bound volumes pertaining to Frank's memberships, law practice, and lifelong advocacy of civil liberties and racial equality.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the Library by Alfred P. Fernbach of Charlottesville, Virginia, on May 3, 1990 and April 17, 1992.
Biographical/Historical Information
Walter Frank (1882-1969) was a civil liberties lawyer who practiced in the law offices of Kurzman & Frank in New York. He was also vice-chairman of the executive committee of the Citizens Union, a member of the national board of the American Civil Liberties Union, the National Consumers League, and the Citizens League for Industrial Democracy. He received the Citizenship award from the League for Industrial Democracy in 1956 and a citation for exceptional civic service from the Citizens Union in 1966. Throughout his life, Frank was known as an advocate for civil liberties and racial equality, and was very active in trying to meet these goals.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1943-1965, pertaining to the American Civil Liberties Union include correspondence and reports. There are letters from Dorothy Kenyon (1888-1972), December 9, 1942 re the Civil Liberties Defense Fund; Roger N. Baldwin (1884- ), October 17, 1944, re the Railway Mail Association; Varian Fry, January 8, 1956, re ACLU elections; and, John De Jarnette Pemberton, Jr., September 20, 1966 and July 15 & 22, August 1, 1968, re ACLU business and board election results. Other items include the ACLU by-laws, December 3, 1957 and two reports, "Bibliography on Academic Freedom," May 1959 and "The ACLU's 1965 Expansion Program," September 1, 1965. Papers, 1943-1950, relating to the Bar Association consist of numerous reports of the Committee on the Bill of Rights. Papers, 1939-1970, concerning Frank's other civic service include letters and speeches about the League for Industrial Democracy 1956 Award for distinguished public service and the Citizens Union 1966 Award for exceptional civil service. There are letters of congratulations from Dorothy Kenyon (1888-1972) (telegram), Newbold Morris (1902-1966), Karl E. Meyer, Norman (Mattoon) Thomas (1884-1968) (electrostatic copy), and Roger Nash Baldwin (1884- ). Also included are two statements, January 1956, by John Haynes Holmes (1879-1964) and Richard S. Childs, concerning Frank's civic accomplishments. Papers, 1962, concerning the Civil Liberties Center at New York University School of Law, include letters of Norman Dorsen, director, and a report entitled "A Summary of State Decisions on Standing to Challenge Unconstitutional State Action in New York." Papers, 1945-1946, concerning the Equal Rights Amendment contain letters from Dorothy S. McAllister, Chairman of the National Committee to Defeat the Un-Equal Rights Amendment.
Personal correspondence, 1925-1969, of Walter and Adelaide Frank cover a variety of topics. The letters are arranged alphabetically by last name of the correspondent. There is an interesting letter, December 6, 1930, from anarchist Alexander Berkman (1870-1936) in St. Tropez, France, concerning his recent activities and his possible fate. Letters from LeRoy Bowman (1887-1971) discuss his book, tentatively entitled Stumbling Toward Democracy: a grass high view of organization in America, April 6, 1967, and a League for Industrial Democracy election, April 30, 1969. Letters, 1942- 1961, from Abram Lincoln Harris (1899-1963) are rich in relating the feelings and experiences of a black man in the academic world. In a letter of [1948?] he writes about being recommended for a position with tenure at Chicago University, commenting that his "Alma Mater will go very slowly in the matter of giving a Negro a major appointment on the faculty." On July 17, 1949, from London, he relates the conditions of blacks living and working in England and his own experiences with prejudice there. Elinore Morehouse Herrick (1895-1964) and John Haynes Holmes (1879-1964) both comment on the Franks' proposal to share their books with others through a lending process, October 1950. There are also several letters from Holmes about the Roger Baldwin Foundation lectures (July 15, 1952 and May 17, September 15, 1955). There is a letter, October 13, 1939, from Cordell Hull (1871-1955), giving an explanation of the goals and functions of the Department of State, especially its Division of Cultural Relations. He expresses his desire to have cooperation between the government and "the numerous public and private institutions and organizations" in working toward a better understanding between the American people and other countries, and extends an invitation to Frank to participate in a Conference on Inter-American Relations in the Field of Education. A letter, March 19, 1960, from Joseph P. Lash (1909- ), refers to his concerns over Germany's future and his opposition to reunification. Henry Morgenthau (1856-1946) writes on March 23, 1933, in answer to an inquiry concerning a possible Commission to Russia. There are two invitations, one to appear as a guest on Edward R. Murrow's (1908-1965) "This I Believe" Program, and one from Eleanor Roosevelt (1884-1962) for dinner at the White House on January 28, 1941. On September 25, 1946, Gaetano Salvemini (1873-1957) writes in appreciation of a check for the Italian School of Pisa and its part toward "international cooperation." Two letters, June 1 and 22, 1931, from architect William Sanger, concern the College Art Association's desire to exhibit Frank's watercolors, "The Derelict" and "On the Shrewsbury River," in their travelling show. There are also letters from Elmer Rice (1892-1967), Bayard Rustin (1910- ), Wallace Stanley Sayre (1905- 1972), Harbans Singh (1921- ), Norman Thomas (1884-1968), and Jean Starr Untermeyer (1886-1970). A letter, July 26, 1936, signed "Leon," discusses observations made in Leningrad and Moscow, U.S.S.R. following the new constitution. Comments are made on various aspects of life, including work-related areas, housing, and costs; education, particularly libraries and new schools; the existence of art, historical, and industrial museums, and places for entertainment. There are references to the state of flux and the suggestions and criticisms (about the constitution) from many sources.
There are also miscellaneous items including newspaper articles on Adelaide (Schulkind) and Walter Frank, certificates of appointment, 1921 and 1928, and poetry concerning a visit to Mexico. In addition, there are several photographs of Frank, both in work and social settings and accepting the L.I.D. 1956 Award. Papers, 1942-1947, concerning Powers of Attorney include several letters from Randolph Evernghim Paul (1890- 1956) and D. Spencer Bliss ( -1950). Of special interest are letters, 1930-1931, of Katherine Anne Porter while in Mexico. The three letters written to Frank are very open and revealing, discussing various aspects of her writing and immediate plans for the future. Porter was in Mexico following the advise of her physician to go to a warmer climate. Apparently, Frank was her benefactor, as she writes "without your help I could not have stayed here so long...," and asks for an extension of the help. She explains that she has applied for the Guggenheim Fellowship but won't hear anything until March, and meanwhile has had various offers from magazines. She expresses her belief that she will be able to finish her novel [ Thieves' Market] and reach a healthy state if allowed to stay a few months more in Mexico. She refers to being a little homesick and missing her friend Becky [Crawford]. Also, in her letter of December 14, 1930, she notes that she is sending an inscribed copy of her Flowering Judas. In her letter of January 26, 1931, she relates how she wrote and completed her first story, "Maria Concepcion," discusses her view of limited editions, and describes events during the earthquake that nearly destroyed Oaxaca, Mexico. Her letter of April 7, 1931, reveals that she has been accepted for the Guggenheim Fellowship, and that she will be ready to begin her second novel in October. There are also fifteen snapshots of scenes in Mexico, including three of Porter.
Professional Correspondence includes letters from Newbold Morris (1902-1966), May 16, 1961; Stanley Myer Isaacs (1882-1962), September 15, 1961; Robert M. Morgenthau, January 26, 1967; Alan C. Swan, University of Chicago about the Abram L. Harris Scholarship Fund, December 7, 1967; and, Algernon D. Black, January 3, 1963 and December 11, 1967.
Material on Charlotte Wilder includes two letters and a transcript of an article, November 1, 1934, relating the relationship between Frank and Wilder. In a letter dated "Friday," she encloses ten of her poems and discusses her manner of writing prose. There are also two letters from Evelyn Scott with the Wilder material.
Among the bound volumes are two sets of family journals, "Our Days" (1957-1967) and "Woodland House Log" (1949-1957). Correspondents found among the pages in "Our Days" include Algernon D. Black re the Encampment for Citizenship to provide a scholarship in the name of Stanley Isaacs, June 14, 1965; Hugh H. Smythe, Ambassador-designate to Syria, August 12, 1965; Noah Greenberg (1919-1966) of New York Pro Musica, January 4, 1966; Asa Philip Randolph (1889- ), October 25, 1966; and, Alfred P. Fernbach (1915- ), October 31, 1966. The "Woodland House Log" contains letters from Norman Thomas (1884-1968), February 7, 1952 and December 6 & 9, 1954; Adlai Ewing Stevenson (1900-1965), November 12, 1952; and, Pauli Murray (1910- ), January 20, 1957. The bound volumes also include tributes to Walter Frank, entitled "Inter-State Walter Frank Birthday Anniversary Record/February 10, 1957" and "Walter Frank Citizen Extraordinary/February 10, 1962." The 1957 volume includes congratulations from Norman Thomas (1884-1968), Jean Starr Untermeyer (1886-1970), Morris and Margaret Ernst, David W. and Betty Schulkind, Stanley W. and Dorothy Dunbar Walker, Lillian A. Seidel, John Haynes Holmes (1879-1964), James M. Frank, "Ben W. Huebsch (1876-1964) and Alfhild, LeRoy Bowman (1887-1971) and Garda, and Pat[rick Murphy Malin]. There are also photographs of members of the Frank, Fernbach, and Rowan family. Correspondents found in the 1962 volume include: Allan Knight Chalmers (1897-1972), Charles Einstein, Alfred Phillip Fernbach (1915- ), James N. Frank, Joseph G. Glass, John Haynes Holmes (1897-1964), "Ben" W. Huebsch (1876-1964), Stanley Myer Isaacs (1882-1962), John Paul Jones (1898-1965) and Helen Agnes Reed Jones, Elmer Rice (1892-1967), Leo Rothschild, Lillian A. Seidel, David W. Schulkind, Norman Thomas (1884-1968), Jean Starr Untermeyer (1886-1970), Karl E. Meyer, Stanley W. and Dorothy Dunbar Walker, and Dorothy Kenyon (1888-1972).
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by subject.
Contents List
- American Civil Liberties Union 1943-1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
- American Humanist Association 1957-1961 (Box 1)
- Bar Association 1943-1950 (Box 1)
- Birthday Celebrations for Walter Frank 1952-1962 (Box 1)
- Citizens Union 1929-1966 (Box 1)
- Civic Service 1939-1970 (Box 1)
- Civil Liberties Center 1962 (Box 1)
- Croton River at Goldens Bridge 1921-1927 (Box 1)
- Equal Rights Amendment 1945-1946 (Box 2)
- In Honor of Walter Frank 1950 (Box 2)
- Law Reform 1928-1950 (Box 2)
- Legal Papers re Philip Frank Estate 1924-1925 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous 1921-1969, n.d. (Box 2)
- Personal Correspondence of Walter and Adelaide Frank 1925-1969 (Box 2)
- Photographs of Walter and Adelaide Frank 1956-1966, n.d. (Box 2)
- Katherine Anne Porter 1930-1931 (Box 2)
- Powers of Appointment and related Tax Laws 1942-1947 (Box 2)
- Printed 1917-1963 (Box 2)
- Professional Correspondence of Walter Frank 1955-1968 (Box 2)
- Charlotte Wilder 1934-1935, n.d. (Box 2)
- "Our Days" 1957-1964, 3 folders
- "Our Days" 1965-1967, 2 folders
- "Woodland House Log" 1949-1957, 2 folders
- Poems and Songs of Philip Frank in honor of his wife Josephine and family 1866-1898
- Scrapbook, "Walter Frank's Journal" 1882-1932, bound volume
- "Inter-State Walter Frank Birthday Anniversary Record/February 10, 1957" 1957, bound volume
- "Walter Frank Citizen Extraordinary/February 10, 1962" 1962, bound volume